<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel>
<title>Giovanni's Diary Ephemeris</title>
<link>giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/ephemeris.html</link>
<description><![CDATA[Ephemeris (ἐφημερίς) is an ancient greek word meaning diary, journal. In astronomy, ephemeris refers to a book of tables describing the trajectory of astronomical objects. Here I will keep a sort of public diary with various thoughts and stuff I find interesting for the record.]]></description>
<item>
<title>2025-03-16</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-03-16.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>16 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I was taking a walk in my neighbourhood, there is not much too see
here. A couple of small parks, some triees, and mostly residential
houses. Yesterday I was watching a live of Prod. in real time, he was
just answering some questions from chat. He is such an interesting
and unique person, let me elaborate. Some people know him for his
philosophy videos, I belive he has a formal education in philosophy
and he often records his walks where he openly shared hit thoughts.
He lives a simple life in the mountain, with little to no human
contact or even electricity. Some other people know him for his
emacs videos: he is a maintainer of some well-known pacakges and he is
surely very knowledgable about his emacs-craft. He brings this two
worlds togheter, this is why I think he is so unique.
I started to watch his emacs videos and became interested into the
philosophy ones. What strikes me is his self aweareness. Just by
talking, he uncovered some of my own inner hazards and helped me
get more aware of them.
</p>

<p>
[ Here I have redacted some pages where I reflect about myself, I
am still unsure on how much to share here so I will redact this for
now ]
</p>

<p>
Another point of reflection of this walk was history and searching
through old stuff. In the park where I usually go there is a small
wooden shelf under some stone structure. It is one of those shelfes
where people may take or leave any book. I always stop there to see
new books and If something interests me I would take it home for
some time. Some of the books are narrative, some of them are
didactical books, most of them are very old. What fascinates me is how
those pieces of paper can open a window into the past and look at
the world from a totally different prospective. For example, there
was a local newspaper from a lot of time ago, it was one of the
first with colored ink. It looked like from another era, totally
another style. I imagined how people reading this newspaper looked
like and I find it peaceful. I am attracted to a simpler life,
and I enjoy those thoughts.
</p>

<p>
[ Here I redacted some more pages, but basically I was getting
inspired to start writing some stories ]
</p>

<p>
Anyway, I am heading back home right now. I updated my todo list with
some stuff.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-03-19</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-03-19.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>19 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I was reading the post "On the Stoic harmony with nature" of Prod
where he talks of phylosophy, I wanted to save it here for the record
because it was such an interesting read:
</p>

<p>
In Greece we have a saying that comes to us from antiquity: “nothing
bad not intermixed with good” (ουδέν κακόν αμιγές καλού). A liberal
translation is “there is no pure evil in this world as everything we
find that is bad always has some good mixed into it.” The opposite is
also true, namely, that all good things have some bad inherent to them.
</p>

<p>
[&#x2026;]
</p>

<p>
In nature things happen when they are meant to. Consider how trees
blossom when their spring arrives, bears hibernate during winter, rain
drops when there are clouds, and so on. No phenomenon can be decoupled
from its fundamentals and, by extension, no event can be independent
of the totality of phenomena. The same is true for the human condition,
though we may lack that kind of patience in our deeds to see how some
eventuality is the result of dynamics that build up over time.
</p>

<p>
[&#x2026;]
</p>

<p>
The Greek word for “nature” is “physis” (φύσις) which refers to things
that grow. They develop organically, as noted above, and have a life
of their own that is couched in terms of the cosmic continuum of life:
they are all coexistent and interdependent. To live in accordance with
nature, then, is to go with the flow of the prevailing conditions,
else to be adaptable. When trees cannot grow directly upward because
some obstacle is in their way, they grow sideways, circumventing the
problem.
</p>

<p>
Compare this to the attitude of forcing things to happen, of declaring
our wants, and trying to implement them regardless of the prevailing
conditions. If the tree insists on only going straight up, then it
will perish. Same principle for humans. What would my life be like
had I insisted on becoming a footballer and did not show the requisite
adaptability to try new things and to ultimately find value in them?
I would probably be miserable the whole time, as I would be fighting
against forces I could not overcome, never to realise my goal, and
never to have the necessary openness to take in what the world was
showing me.
</p>

<p>
End note: thank you Prod for your wisdom.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-03-23</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-03-23.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>23 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I just wanted to share a thing that made me laugh for some time. I
am currently developing a kubernetes application for my ""internship"",
most of the code is in go, and some is in c. I am not an expert in go,
however the application is INCREDIBLY slow to compile and it weights
A LOT for being just a simple client that makes some api calls to
kubernetes. So, I was reporting this to one of my "supervisors":
</p>

<pre class="example">
Me:
The only complaint I have at the moment is that building the operator
inside the docker container before pushing it to the local repository
takes 105 seconds on average on my laptop (i3-1110G4 CPU) and it
weights 92M which is outrageous (by comparison, my linux kernel 6.11.4
image is 16M), and I am using the default makefile from operator-sdk...
I guess this is because operator-sdk downloaded a big number of
dependencies but I wonder if the application actually needs all of them
or if they can be compiled once and dynamically linked later to speed
up compile times.
</pre>

<p>
I felt this was a reasonable thing to complain. I got this in response:
</p>

<pre class="example">
Well, I see your point, but it's considered a "feature" of Go to
produce a single binary, which includes all dependencies, but this
also makes the binaries huge :'D
</pre>

<p>
A FEATURE? I really don't know if I should take this language
seriously or just laught at it, beacuse many things are just laughable.
Being able to dynamically link executable has always been one of the
most basic things, it is incredible to me that people consider go as
a language for system programming. Maybe I am just too used to C, but
com' on I cannot have the most simple client of 92MB!
I still have the best intentions of keep learning and write ideomatic
code in go, maybe I just have to understand that modern software has
to suck to become a real go programmer.
</p>

<p>
Also I call this ""intenship"" with many quotes because I am basically
developing this application completely on my own, my teacher is not
even answering my mails. Many of my fellow colleagues are in the same
situation. Still, I was not surpriced since I always think realistically
and honestly I didn't expect much from university, but it surely is
sad. The funny thing is that the internship was supposed to happen with
a company, but then they said it could not continue with them for
various legal reasons (I had to move to the USA) so I am proceeding to
develop what I was suppoed to on my own.
</p>

<p>
Emacs lisp is very cool, I am writing tiny-rss and I am having a lot
of fun. Firther, today I have redesigned by blog and it looks awesome,
exactly what I wanted! It's really really simple, which I find
aesthetically pleasing.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-03-24</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-03-24.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>24 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Today I stumbled across some really interesting things and I wanted to
share it via this document. If you know me, I am subscribed to quite a
number of mailing lists, one of them being gmane announce. There isn't
a particular reason why I subscribed to this other than curiosity,
messages are rare so it does not bother me.
</p>

<p>
Today a new mailing list was registered for the community around
XEphem. Now, I didn't know what was XEphem prior to reading this
mailing list, but now I am super happy to have discovered it. EXphem
is a "scientific-grade interactive astronomical ephemeris package".
The word Ephemeris comes from greek and it means diary or journal.
In astronomy, it refers to a book of tables describing the trajectory
of astronomical objects. Those books were used and are still used
today (in a more modern fashion) to navigate the sky and to study
celestial bodies.
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://xephem.github.io/XEphem/Site/xephem.html">XEphem</a> is a powerful MIT licensed software with so many
functionalities and a look from the 90', you know this is a good
software. Even though it is practically useless to me, I started
playing with the program. Is is packaged on variaous linux
distributions and even on other operating systems such as FreeBSD and
Solaris. It looks amazing to me, I encourage you to take a look at it,
it is full of functionalities. Also the program is written in C,
beautiful C.
</p>

<p>
I then read the wikipedia page and discovered so many things. First,
cilivizations have been making ephemeris since the Babylonians in the
1st millennium BC. Moreover, the term "epoch" in astronomy refers to
a moment in time used as a reference point for some other astronomical
quantity, what is interesting is that the calendars used in astronomy
are not the same as the terrestrial ones, so sometimes there are
funny dates such as January 0.
</p>

<p>
Overall, it was fun going on a different place where I know close to
nothing about and be intrigued this much like a kid.
</p>

<p>
Some other interesting things. Someone made a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/emacs/comments/1jhjgnu/the_book_of_the_church_of_emacs_satirical_ten/">funny reddit post</a> about
the 10 rules of the emacs church that was fun to read. Also, another
blogger I follow shared some photos of flowers in his city and I feel
inspired to do the same in the following days.
</p>

<p>
One last thing. Today Linux 6.14 released and the usual message from
Linus made me laugh:
</p>

<pre class="example">
So it's early Monday morning (well - early for me, I'm not really a
morning person), and I'd love to have some good excuse for why I
didn't do the 6.14 release yesterday on my regular Sunday afternoon
release schedule. 

I'd like to say that some important last-minute thing came up and
delayed things. 

But no. It's just pure incompetence. 
</pre>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-04-03</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-04-03.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>03 Apr 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I did so many things this week, I don't know where to start.
</p>

<p>
I switched my window manager from i3 to <a href="https://github.com/San7o/dwm">dwm</a>. The cool thing about dwm
is that there is no configuration file, instead you have to change
the C cource code and recompile it. Moreover, dwm is very very
minimal and for most of the things you would need to write custom code,
such as full screen, startup programs and different tiling arrangements.
It is possible to customize it because it is very minimali, abour 2000
lines of code, which is amazing. I didn't read the entire source yet
but I will soon because it is very educational.
</p>

<p>
Another thing, I downloaded Wikipedia, at least some sections of it.
You can download wikipedia to read it offline, and I REALLY like this.
I am becoming more and more independent from the internet every day and
I am enjoying my offline sessions. I have written <a href="../programming/offline-programming.html">offline programming</a>
where I talk about this, I used kiwis to download and view the
compressed wikipedia data.
</p>

<p>
I tried to get into space photography by downloading some images from
JWST and edited them. You can download the .fits file from the <a href="https://mast.stsci.edu/portal/Mashup/Clients/Mast/Portal.html">mast</a>
portal, then you need to fix the colors with some stretch filters.
I used <a href="https://siril.org/">siril</a> for this, which is very powerful but I would prefer
something simpler. I then exported the modified .fits into .tif and
added colors with gimp. The result is not that great but it's a start.
</p>


<div id="org7a9dc9c" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/jwst-ngc-3132.jpeg" alt="jwst-ngc-3132.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>NGC 3132 Nebula</p>
</div>

<p>
Yesterday there was the nintendo direct where they announced the
switch 2. I am not a really big fan of Nintendo, being a PC gamer
for my whole life, but the interesting news is that Silk Song exists
and FromSoftware will release a new game similar to bloodborne in style&#x2026;
exclusive for the nintendo switch&#x2026; (sight). Also two new chapters
of deltarune (which I never player but I want to since it is very short).
</p>

<p>
I have been writing machine learning algorithms, such as <a href="https://gist.github.com/San7o/4bfe69a9e1eb251d5267d8b74ff73dda">KNN</a> and the
<a href="https://gist.github.com/San7o/da2efc84eb3e7c8bdbefbd540c8cfbea">perceptron</a>. I am particularly enjoying the math behind everything.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-04-07</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-04-07.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>07 Apr 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I want to record some updates on what I have been working on, so here
they are.
</p>

<p>
In the last few days I spent some time into improving this website,
both in presentation and in the content. More specifically, I added an
interactive map in the Surrounding page using OpenStreetmap which is
pretty cool. Further, I am generating a PDF book by translating the
org files into latex and then to pdf, which still needs some work on
the typography.
</p>

<p>
This weekend I went in Mount Celva which was a very enjoyable hike,
visiting World War I fortresses close to the city, and I have written
a new entry in Surroundings. I have to say that I am really enjoying
writing this blog, I feel a slight sense of proudness even though I
know there is so much to improve.
</p>

<p>
I am getting into history, perhaps inspired by the walk in the
fortresses, so I started looking for ways to learn more. I concluded
that the most fun way to learn history would be to read directly
sources archived from the past, and trying to piece together the story
of the places when I visit them, similar to trying to discover the
lore of a videogame such as Dark Souls. You have no idea how much I
like this gamification of history.
</p>

<p>
Thankfully, there are many preservation programs of old documents and
everyday items from the past in my city, with even an online database
(really unexpected from the public sector). I guess I will try to play
the historian when I have the opportunity. I really value the effort
people make to document history, I think it is a very important
thing. I also started watching the documentary series <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d2lJUOv0hLA&amp;list=PLR7yrLMHm11XAuYuZMPHPn9HznxQ40y_f">Fall of
Civilizations</a> on youtube which I really enjoy, episodes are more
that 3 hours long so it's a lot to enjoy.
</p>


<div id="orgea06ce9" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/library-window.jpg" alt="library-window.jpg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>At the historical museum's library</p>
</div>

<p>
I listened to a choir singing in a local church. The songs were from
the 12th or 13th century with some elements of instruments from the
14th centuty. Really fascinating, during those times the melody was
secondary to the words and was slow and repeating, leaving for a
contemplative feel. Churches were a natural echo chamber to power the
sound of the voice. It also reminded me of the videogame Kingdome Come
Deliveranche which I am following a gameplay of on youtube, I would
play it if I had time and a decent computer.
</p>


<div id="orgfdf46a1" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/choir.jpg" alt="choir.jpg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Choir singing</p>
</div>

<p>
I finished reading "Lunario Sentimentale" by Mauro Corona, it is a
testimony to a past time that is now disappearing, therefore it is
really valuable and it will keep living in the words of this book. I
will write a page on this blog soon.
</p>

<p>
This week I didn't do any programming except some lisp for this website.
On a sidenote, I don't feel really motivated lately so I am trying to
switch things up and try new ideas.
</p>

<p>
One last thing, I want to open a section for photography on this
website. I have hundreds of gigabytes of photos on various hardrives,
I want to put some images here.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-04-19</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-04-19.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>19 Apr 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
It's been some time since my last publication here and stuff have been
piling up, so here is a summary of what I have been playing with
lately.
</p>

<p>
For my Surrounding series, I am converting the org files into latex to
generate a pdf. Last week I wanted to improve the presentation of the
book to make it look more professional, so I started learning more
about typography and paging. While researching for online
documentation and learning materials, I discovered what is probably
one of the best latex books ever, <a href="https://archive.org/details/B-001-002-139">The TexBook</a> by Donald E. Knuth. This
book is amazing, it explains how tex works to an audience of any
experteese by having secions labeled by difficulty and experience
needed to understand it. It is safe to say that even if you have been
writing tex for some years, you would still have plenty to learn from
this book. Moreover, the text is filled with funny jokes and
interesting trivias. Did you know that the name "tex" originates from
greek "τέχ" which means both art and technology?
</p>

<p>
Since we are talking about greek, last week I became interested in
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism">Stoicism</a> as a philosofy for my own life when times get hard, so I have
been reading Marcus Aurelious' Meditations and taking notes. Another
good source is Seneca's <a href="https://www.lettersfromastoic.net">letters</a>. Briefly, the doctrine of stoicism is
based on the idea that a happy man is a man that lives with virtue. A
vrituous man is someone that does not follow pelasure and recreational
activities, "To be violently drawn and moved by the lusts and desires
of the soul, is proper to wild beasts an monsters". A virtuous man is
someone that listens to everybody, that doesn't talk too much but not
too little, is thankful to others, rigid when he needs to be.
</p>

<p>
There is this idea in many greek philosophies about a "correct" way to
live, stoicism extends this by accepting what we are not in control of
and working hard on what we can. I have been struggling with this
recently since there are many things I have no control over which are
giving me great anxiety, and this period in particular is very
intense.  Almost three years ago I read Aristotele's Ethics and he
also talks about virtue in great details by identifying every type of
virtue a man should have. I remember trying to take the best of his
doctrine with me but I lost motivation and now I want to explore this
again.
</p>

<p>
One last greek thing, I really enjoyed the video about
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZXNIgHov0Nk">The $2 Million Lost Book of Archimedes</a>. It talks about the history
of a book which contained some groundbreaking math research from
Archimedes and barely survived time.
</p>

<p>
Math is fascinating. Because of some of my university courses this
semester, I needed to sharpen my multivariable calculus skills so I
have been following <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PxCxlsl_YwY&amp;list=PL4C4C8A7D06566F38">MIT's 18.02 Multivarible Calculus</a> from 2007. I
have to say that I really enjoy math when I don't need to give an
exam soon.
</p>

<p>
Last week there has been a showcase of old computers in the library of
my university: original hardware running Microsoft's DOS and other
operating systems from that time. Computers looked so different, maybe
I am just idealizing a period that has been so important in the
history of computer science that I did not experience, but I really
like the esthetics. I realized that I didn't know anything about DOS
or old hardware since I have always used Unix-like operating systems.
Sadly there was no Unix in the showcase so I felt unacculturated about
the industry I should be an expert of.  Fortunately, most of the
computers were working and some had a physical manual, so I started
reading a manual and played with the DOS.
</p>

<p>
I wanted to create a simple executable "shell" script, which in dos id
called a BAT file. From the manual I learned to edit with EDLIN which
resembles Thompson's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed_(software)">ed</a> text editor (that would later turn into vi and
vim). The program would just use DIR to list the contents of a folder,
I would then execute it with BATCH but I failed to save it because the
floppy disk I was using was in read only mode. I gave up trying
because I was already at the computer for some time.
</p>

<p>
I reinstalled linux from scratch on my desktop pc, this time with the
automated installer because I already compiled it once and It took a
long time. Everything went smootly and the computer was able to boot
and connect to the internet in just one evening, incredible.
Hopefully the automated BLFS will work as flawlessly.
</p>

<p>
Meanwhile, the joint between the screen of my laptop and the rest of
my laptop broke and I cannot open the screen much otherwise it may
break completely.  Honestly, this HP laptop really lasted and endured
a lot, so I am not really surprised that his time would come to an
end. Still, I am a bit frustrated with modern laptops, this is why I
only buy really cheap ones. I have my laptop on my back 24/7 and I
prefer something that is not a big deal if it breaks rather than one
of those expensive laptops with pretty screens that would cost me a
fortune. I grow up with a desktop PC so I consider the desktop as the
powerful computer and the laptop as a client / browser.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-05-14 - The role of theater in my life</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-05-14.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>14 May 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Today I went to theater as a spectator after exactly one year since
the last time I step in a stage (and I was an actor!), which made me
reflect on the role of theater in my life and the fact that its time
has come to an end for me. I feel like I have no interest to enter a
theater on my own and I surely don't have the time and mental space to
participate anymore. This moment concludes a journey of 4 years where
theater was a part of my life and now it's not, I will now explain my
journey and my thoughts.
</p>

<p>
I started theater in my last year of high school and I consider this
one of my bravest decision I ever did. I was a very introverted and
shy person (still am) and I was constantly blocked by my own self
doubt and a lack of social skills. At least I was doing great at CTF
competitions :). In the summer between my fourth and fifth (last) year
of high school I was at a point where I needed to get out there and
push myself hard, so I did and one of the things was joining a theater
class organized by my school. Surely the fact that everything was
setup by my school reduced friction. In fact, I consider myself lucky
because many schools do not have a theater group and mine had just
been created one or two years prior. If it weren't in the school I
probably would have never joined. So I was in theater, actually there
was a short creative writing class before that with the same people so
I got introduced to the group. My god that felt awkward at first, but
I slowly became more comfortable with the exercises and with the
group. By the end, going to the lessons was surely my favorite
activity (after installing Linux everywhere obviously) and it gave me
a lot of motivation and self confidence. I have to say that the
teachers were truly amazing, so was the group and the exercises. My
best memories of high school are all from theater.
</p>

<p>
But life moves on and I moved to another city far from home to pursue
my bachelor degree in computer science. My first year was a year of
great change and discovery, and I decided to keep doing theater. I
joined a local group I found via some fliers hoping to relive some
stress from university. But I was really stressed and pressured daily
so I could not fully enjoy it. Moreover, the experience was completely
different and instead of doing classic theater "creative" exercises,
we were tasked to create our own show by the end of the course. This
was a different thing than the previous year and, while it was not
bad, it was not great neither. I am perfectly conscious that the main
reason for why I didn't enjoy it It's my own fault: I was unable to let
go of myself and university was giving me a constant level of anxiety
and pressure that sat on me at any moment. The people were great too
but as I said I was the principal cause of friction.
</p>

<p>
It's now my second year of university and I decided to try theater
again, this time with another group. And none other that ATU which I
knew was the best of the best, and it was. I got selected in the group
and the lessons started, each Monday evening, in a huge theater all
for ourselves. This was a step higher than anything that I had ever
tried before, both in terms of "professionalism" and intensity.  And
surely it was intense, too much intense for me. The group was a really
active and strong one, I felt like I was the only introverted in the
room and that made me distance from the rest. Let's say that I felt
this distance increasing more and more as time passed, in particular I
discovered how much of a calm and silent person I am and how much I
really felt uncomfortable around such loud and excited people. So far
I have always kept pushing myself to get out of my own "cage" and
socialize with others, but this group completely smashed the limits
until it had the opposite effect of what It should have had giving me
a lot of anxiety. Furthermore, as the final play was getting closer,
the intensity of the lessons kept increasing. So were my university
classes and the date of the exams. By the end of the class, I was
totally overworked, sleep-deprived, stressed and anxious to the point
where this led me to a huge burnout. I was not meant to do theater, I
thought.
</p>

<p>
And so I didn't try again another year and I decided to focus on my
studies, leaving behind everything else. It's now been I year since I
stepped into a theater and I have to say that the distance between
theater and me kept increasing every day. The distance between that
life of constant stimulus and excitement, and my life of stability and
peacefulness are not compatible anymore. I never wanted that life, it
does not feel natural to me.
</p>

<p>
Doing all those years of theater has been a great experience of
discovering myself, the good and the bad.  As I transition from an
university student to a worker, I have so much things to think about
that I can't take some more. I don't feel like I have the motivation
since I am now driven by different ideals. Either way, doing theater
helped me change the course of my life and I will keep this memory in
my heart, with some bitterness and sadness that it came to an end.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-05-15 - Writing Giovanni's Diary</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-05-15.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>15 May 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Today I took some time to reflect on how much I enjoy writing this
public diary. I feel like it is one of those personal projects that I
will keep maintaining for a long time, therefore I should take care
of making the diary grow organically while keeping it structured and
easy to navigate.
</p>

<p>
I dedicate some time every day to maintaining this blog, so it is
always in the back of my mind. This morning I implemented some
improvements, in particular I changed the favicon showing the letter
"G" from an ugly hand (mouse) drawing in an 32x32 grid to a cool
Blackboard bold letter. You may recognize the font since it is the
famous Latex's "\mathbb" to denote number sets.
</p>


<div id="org749e593" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/logo-old.png" alt="logo-old.png" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Old favicon</p>
</div>


<div id="org08af150" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/logo-new.png" alt="logo-new.png" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>New favicon</p>
</div>

<p>
Additionally I included some meta properties on the head section of
the html in every page so that the new logo gets displayed as the link
preview when you are sending the link somewhere such as discord, with
a short description of the website. I then added some pages and went
back to studying. Still, I was not done for the day as I began
thinking about other things that could be improved and reflecting on
the project.
</p>

<p>
First of all, when I just want to work on something naturally means
that I am really enjoying it. Secondly, I like the long term goal
of the project of documenting my time now. As I was wandering about
how to improve this, I thought I could take inspiration from some
other people that are making a similar thing, so I began searching
the web.
</p>

<p>
Coincidentally (or maybe not) this same morning I saw a cool website
on HackerNews - <a href="https://neal.fun/internet-artifacts/">Internet Artifacts</a> - which shows some of the most
important moments and innovations in the early years of the internet.
One of them in particular cached my attention, it was one of the
first blogs ever "Justin's Links from the Underground" which pioneered
the concept of sharing everything online. I thought it was cool and I
kept going with my day, but I remembered about this blog while I was
seeking inspiration to improve mine so I dig deeper.
</p>

<p>
To be clear, I don't like the modern way of sharing everything online,
in fact I am totally the opposite. I rarely use social media, maybe
once or twice a month, other than HackerNews or a bunch of mailing
lists. Instead, here I can write long form content and I can be more
thoughtful and considerate about what I publish online while
respecting the privacy of others. Something that I feel like is missing
in the dopamine-centric corporate-controlled digital world we live in.
</p>

<p>
I didn't know about Justin's website and after navigating it for about
20 minutes it felt like a huge maze. I watched a nice documentary
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AxD4mqFtySQ">overshare: the links.net story</a> which tells his story and it was really
interesting, but I wanted to find something else for
inspiration. Again I started asking the internet and the internet
answered: I found some communities that referred to themselves as
"<a href="https://tildeverse.org/">tildes</a>" who are centered around a shared Linux server. How it works
is that you get access to the machine and you can start doing whatever
you want. This server then becomes a social place do share things and
do stuff together, really amazing and nerdy! Obviously I immediately
felt this was the thing for me and I started observing other people's
pages, but I have to say that the big majority are underdeveloped or
even empty. Still, I want to get closer to those communities because
they are cool.
</p>

<p>
At the end of the day I didn't find someone to take inspiration from,
but I found some communities to get motivation and I feel lucky about
it. I realized that want to promote the routine of keeping a diary or
a blog through my writings and help others with the technical details
since this is waht I know best.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-05-18 - Self Hosting</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-05-18.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>18 May 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Hi,
</p>

<p>
for unknown reasons, today I woke up with a lot of motivation to self
host a bunch of services. And I know I have a lot to study and I need
to prepare for the exams, but I thought I could install some things
while studying (which did not work, but I at least I studied
afterwards).
</p>

<p>
Every time I think about self hosting, the first thing that comes to
my mind is the fact that I cannot do it right now: first I cannot do
port forwarding since I can't control the router of my dormitory,
secondly the router uses the university's network which blocks a lot
of traffic. This means that I cannot just open some port and access it
on another machine, even if I am on the same network. Alternatively I
could use a VPN, but it would probably cost a few bucks and I cannot
afford to have any more expenses now, especially for recreational (and
frankly useless) projects like this. This morning I searched the web
for free VPNs and I found <a href="https://tailscale.com/">tailscale</a> which lets me connect up to 100
devices on the same network with the free plan. I am not affiliated to
them in any way but I have to say that the service is amazing and it
works beautifully, kudos to them.
</p>

<p>
Now that I can connect to my other computers remotely, I can have some
fun. The computer I wanted to use as a server is my old desktop: it
has an i5-6600K, 16GB DDR4, NVIDIA 1060 3G, 1TB M.2 SSD and 10 years
of experience in the trenches. This was my first (and only) desktop
computer I got when I was 12. I grew up with it, I played hundreds of
games, spent days and nights on discord and it is still working
nicely. It has installed Fedora 42 on the M.2 and Linux From Scratch
on another SSD. So I booted up fedora, connected the network and ssh
into it from my laptop. Time to have fun.
</p>

<p>
Since my laptop is not really powerful, the first thing I did was
installing ollama to play with some models. In particular, I installed
llama3.2:3B and qwen2.5:3B (7B is already too slow, and more that this
does not work at all). The difference in quality from last year's
models is really incredible: 3B parameters were basically useless a
few months ago and now they are good enough to use daily on my 10 year
old computer, truly amazing. After installing the model, I wanted some
kind of frontend to use and I downloaded <a href="https://docs.openwebui.com/">Open WebUI</a>. Installing it
felt dystopic, it downloaded literally thousands of dependencies!
Then, after downloading half of the pip repository, you can run the
program just to download a few other hundreds of dependencies. All of
this for a website with a text field that sends the text to an api,
disgusting. But after all the application (to my surprise) managed to
run and it was working flawlessly. It is probably the most feature
rich LLM frontend out there, I have to say, but it is also quite
bloated. Still, I don't feel comfortable running an application that
depends on billions of lines of python and javascript code so I will
seek something else.
</p>

<p>
Another thing I installed is a minecraft server. I haven't played
minecraft in a while (at least a few years) and I know they added so
many things, playing it now would be like rediscovering everything
from scratch. But for for today I have plenty to do so I just installed
the server, joined to make sure it worked and moved on.
</p>

<p>
I then wanted some kind of filemanager, but my experience was even
worse than with Open WebUI. Most of the things I found online were
completely bloated and difficult to install. Some of them didn't work
because of various dependencies issues which I did not dare to
debug. Fortunately, there is some good and I found <a href="https://tinyfilemanager.github.io/">Tiny File Manager</a>
which is a single php file that implements the entire web app. I think
many project should take this as an example: you get a full file
manager just by creating a php server and accessing that file. Easy.
</p>

<p>
I also wanted to install <a href="https://git.zx2c4.com/cgit/about/">cgit</a> as a frontend to access all my
repositories. It took some time and struggles, I first tried to make
it work with nginx but apparently It does not natively support CGI and
I found issues in making the communication to the socket so I switched
to apache and it worked well. I had some other issues with file
permissions which I sort of solved, wonderful.
</p>

<p>
Going forward, I want to upgrade my system and have a NAS and a rack,
when I will have an economical possibility. I would also like to use
my setup as a node to host some community services such as a mastodon
node or contribute to a research project like the CENR's <a href="https://lhcathome.web.cern.ch/">@home</a>
projects.
</p>

<p>
I am also taking some time to reflect on the importance of self
hosting and being independent from big predatory corporations. We are
all so dependent on them and this makes us vulnerable and makes them
money, If I can be a little more independent I will also be a little
happier.
</p>

<p>
&#x2013; Giovanni
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-05-19 - Setting up a local cluster</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-05-19.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>19 May 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Hi,
</p>

<p>
today I spent most of my day setting up a local cluster for
kubernetes.  I thought this would be nice and simple but it wasn't,
let me tell you why.
</p>

<p>
The reason why I wanted to have my own custom cluster is mostly
because I don't like popular solutions based on virtual machines. I
have always done all my development in a cluster with Kind and that
has been awesome, Kind is light weight and easy to setup. However,
Kind uses docker containers and it works only locally. For my
application, I need to test it on various cluster topologies,
especially in multiple nodes running different kernels. I have this
requirement because my application behaves differently based on the
number of running kernels in the cluster since I need to load eBPF
programs in the kernel.
</p>

<p>
Well, I tried to use Minikube but both my laptop and my Desktop would
completely freeze. Minikube is incredibly resource hungry and a lot of
the drivers do not work at all. Additionally, I have so many problems
on running particular topologies with multiple nodes and different
images. I think Minikube is slow and heavy, and buggy. The
alternatives do not satisfy me for similar reasons: I knew that I
could setup a simple and light cluster on my own and have any kind of
configuration I wanted, like 2 nodes on my desktop, one on my laptop
and another one on my other laptop for example. So I started setting
up everything by myself.
</p>

<p>
My vision is to have any number of Linux images running via qemu and
KVM, all connected to the same network. The images would then run the
various kubernetes daemons and I would control everything from a
tmuxed terminal. All of this is managed centrally using a bunch of
scripts. Since I am bootstrapping everything, I have full control on
any part of my cluster, making it simple to hack. However, I have to
say that setting up this did not went exactly smoothly.
</p>

<p>
To make the machines communicate with the internet and themselves I
needed to setup some tap interface and connect them via a bridge. You
need to do this correctly in order to make everything work, my final
script to bootstrap the interface is the following:
</p>

<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-bash"><span style="color: #ff7f24;">#</span><span style="color: #ff7f24;">!/bin/</span><span style="color: #00ffff;">bash</span>
<span style="color: #b0c4de;">set</span> -e

<span style="color: #b0c4de;">echo</span> <span style="color: #ffa07a;">"Creating bridge br0..."</span>

sudo ip link set br0 down 2&gt;/dev/null || true
sudo ip link delete br0 type bridge 2&gt;/dev/null || true

sudo ip link add name br0 type bridge
sudo ip addr add 192.168.50.1/24 dev br0
sudo ip link set br0 up

<span style="color: #b0c4de;">echo</span> 1 | sudo tee /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
sudo iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -s 192.168.50.0/24 ! -o br0 -j MASQUERADE

<span style="color: #00ffff;">for</span> i<span style="color: #00ffff;"> in</span> 0 1; <span style="color: #00ffff;">do</span>
  <span style="color: #eedd82;">tap</span>=<span style="color: #ffa07a;">"tap$i"</span>

  <span style="color: #b0c4de;">echo</span> <span style="color: #ffa07a;">"Setting up $tap..."</span>

  sudo ip link set <span style="color: #ffa07a;">"$tap"</span> down 2&gt;/dev/null || true
  sudo ip tuntap del <span style="color: #ffa07a;">"$tap"</span> mode tap 2&gt;/dev/null || true

  sudo ip tuntap add dev <span style="color: #ffa07a;">"$tap"</span> mode tap
  sudo ip link set <span style="color: #ffa07a;">"$tap"</span> up
  sudo ip link set <span style="color: #ffa07a;">"$tap"</span> master br0
<span style="color: #00ffff;">done</span>

<span style="color: #b0c4de;">echo</span> <span style="color: #ffa07a;">"Bridge and tap devices ready."</span>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
I also made a script to clean everything and can be found on the
<a href="https://github.com/San7o/hive-operator/tree/main/k8s-lab">project's repo</a>. Then I needed to setup a static IP in each machine and
&#x2026; it didn't quite work. The problem was that I also needed to set a
different MAC address for each virtual machine or the TCP/IP stack
could not route the packets&#x2026; that took a LOONG time to figure out
because nothing hinted that this was the problem. I basically tried
random things for 3 hours until this worked, wonderful.
</p>

<p>
Thankfully I endured that and now I am here to tell a beautiful story
instead of being ashamed of my own incompetence. Anyway, now I have a
bunch of VMs all connected to the same network that can ping each other
and the internet. Next time I will make so that they will
automatically install k3s (a kubernetes distribution) and we should be
good to go.
</p>

<p>
Another interesting thing I learned is <a href="https://cloudinit.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html">cloud-init</a> which helps setting
up the userspace of the VMs from an external config file, which looks
like this:
</p>

<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-yaml"><span style="color: #ff7f24;">#</span><span style="color: #ff7f24;">cloud-config</span>
<span style="color: #eedd82;">users</span>:
    - <span style="color: #eedd82;">name</span>: fedora
      <span style="color: #eedd82;">groups</span>: user,wheel
      <span style="color: #eedd82;">hashed_passwd</span>: ...
      <span style="color: #eedd82;">lock_passwd</span>: <span style="color: #7fffd4;">false</span>
      <span style="color: #eedd82;">sudo</span>: ALL=(ALL) NOPASSWD:ALL
<span style="color: #eedd82;">write_files</span>:
  <span style="color: #ff7f24;"># </span><span style="color: #ff7f24;">Enable password authentication in ssh</span>
  - <span style="color: #eedd82;">path</span>: /etc/ssh/sshd_config.d/20-enable-passwords.conf
    <span style="color: #eedd82;">content</span>: |
      <span style="color: #ffa07a;">PasswordAuthentication yes</span>
<span style="color: #eedd82;">runcmd</span>:
  - systemctl restart NetworkManager
  - systemctl restart sshd
  - nmcli connection up static-ens3
</pre>
</div>

<p>
I find this very useful, thank you Fedora for letting me discover
this.
</p>

<p>
The rest of my day was spent signing an enormous amount of documents
for my internship and doing physics exercises at the blackboards in
my university until closing hour, had a lasagna and now back to study
physics.
</p>

<p>
&#x2013; Giovanni
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-05-20 - Struggles with NetworkManager</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-05-20.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>20 May 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Hi,
</p>

<p>
today I continued what I left off yesterday with my local kubernetes
cluster. To recap, I am bootstrapping a local cluster to test a
kubernetes operator and I want to have full control of the cluster
while being easy to hack.
</p>

<p>
Yesterday I spawned up the virtual machines and connected them to the
same network, today I wanted to configure the kubernetes daemons but
something was pissing me off. During the first boot of the machine,
NetworkManager spawns up and looks for available networks for about 1
minute and 30 seconds. But since I need to manually setup a static ip,
it fails and the kernel boots with error messages, not really
pretty. Afterwards, cloud-init setups up the static ip, restarts
NetworkManager and everything would work on next boots. Still this
error was really bothering me, so I tried to fix this.
</p>

<p>
The root of the problem is that I need to set a static ip before
systemd starts the daemons, but I was not able to do so without the
daemons (for example "nmcli connection up" would not work because I
had no NetworkManager running). So I tried setting up the connection
files for NetworkManager and networkd but they would be read only
after initializing the service, so after hanging for one and an half
minutes and showing the error. This problem got me for a while. My
second idea was to disable those services completely but I was not
able to do so before the first boot. And I tried, I even set all the
/etc files with "NetworkManager" in the name to link to /dev/null but
that did not stop the daemon from starting up and failing, so I tried
to override them but that would not work either. I made sure there
were no other services that would depend on NetowrkManager.
</p>

<p>
I looked up online and I found out I could use cloud-init to setup the
network, so I tried that but nothing would happen. I tried to change the
configuration at least 20 times but I got no feedback so I started
thinking that maybe the network configuration was not being applied at
all. Some struggling later I found out that the network configuration
could not stay in the same yaml file as the rest of the configuration,
but it needed to be a separate file. Additionally, I needed to pass
this file to a program called cloud-localds via the &#x2013;network-config
flag. I was using genisoimage previously and it does not have a
similar flag, so I needed to use this other program. Very intuitive
things. So this finally worked and I have a static ip at boot time.
</p>

<p>
Maybe there were many ways to solve this, but for the entire day I
basically got zero feedback on my attempts. Journalctl would not log
anything, genisoimage would not hint that I couldn't configure the
network in the user-data file, it wouldn't say anything even for
spelling mistakes. NetworkManager and systemd was completely ignoring
all the files that I changed or removed, everything was a black box to
me. Error messages are important&#x2026;
</p>

<p>
So finally I could boot the images nicely, I can now setup kubernetes.
I wrote scripts to automate this, then I got missing certificates
and I called it a day, see you tomorrow.
</p>

<p>
The rest of the day I studied flow algorithms and physics. A nice
patch for linux 6.16 promises to improve swap operations by 20-30%
which Is really impressive. Honestly, If I had infinite time and money
I would work all day and night on my operating system, but I have to
do things and start earning a salary so I will leave this for another
day.
</p>

<p>
&#x2013; Giovanni
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-05-26 - Two feelings</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-05-26.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>26 May 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Hi,
</p>

<p>
Today I want to talk about two feelings I experienced in the last 24
hours.  It is nothing rational, just some emotions that took me for
some time and then washed away like water in a river.  In particular,
I want to talk about the feeling of being unfit among others and how I
feel demotivated from my environment.
</p>

<p>
The first emotion is the feeling of unfitness. Yesterday I spent
many hours rewriting several pages of this diary. I was in the mood
of writing, I was focused and it felt really good, I guess a little
writer is growing inside me. I can't help but write honestly.
</p>

<p>
Since I was enjoying this so much, I thought I could share it. Hence,
I started looking for people online with a similar interest. So I
searched the web, dedicating my efforts on discord servers since this
is where many normies hang out. I found two servers, "The Writing Hub"
and "Penpals, Journaling and Stationary", and I began exploring
them. I particularly liked the idea of penpals which is the habit of
writing to somebody with letters or email. This is something I am fit
for: I consume most of my content through mailing lists and blog posts
so I am used to long form written content, and I prefer it this
way. I can express my thoughts and emotions more clearly through
writing, I can take my time to reflect and choose the right words.
</p>

<p>
In the server's presentations page, people would give a brief
description of themselves and their interests. I found many creative
people, artists, music lovers, dancers, painters, etcetera.  Here is
where my self doubts came in. My brain went something like this: "Wow,
all these people do like art, music. It must be easy for them to
socialize. My main interests are things like UNIX operating systems,
like file systems and the Linux's eBPF subsystem&#x2026;". I felt like I'm
too much of a nerd to belong there, and this is one example of more
pervasive thoughts in many other areas. I do not have to fit
everywhere, yet me being me makes everything feel a little lonely and
makes it hard to find a place for me.
</p>

<p>
However I rationalized my feelings and appreciated more the fact that
we are all so different, there is value in interacting with people
from distant backgrounds. Thinking about opposite ideas than yours
will make you better understand others and your own, it makes us
question things we never thought of and refine our reasoning. I
reflected on how much I liked what I do, even if it is really
unpopular among peers. Sometimes I feel lonely in my journey, but
instead of focusing on what I don't have I should think about what
I do have.
</p>

<p>
The second feeling I felt happened just a few hour ago, I was
reflecting on how demotivating university has been. When I wanted to
go to university I had a strong drive to write good software and give
my best, I though this would be a big step up in my programming
journey since in high school I knew nobody that had similar interests
as me. Yet this was not the case, as often I was the most experienced
person in groups. I would see people wibecoding, doing exercises with
chat gpt, not even bothering giving the tiniest effort on the software
they were writing. I don't judge them, I think of others as I would
think for myself and seeing this is not pushing me to improve and give
my best. I have to say that not everything is like this, and I am
overreacting. I can't help but see what my feelings are telling me and
introspect. Yet, it is true that I don't feel pushed to give my best
in, say, contributing to open source or participating in community
projects. For my internship I was completely on my own, little to no
help from my university. I made the best out of it but it would have
been fine to just do a small project and call it a day.
</p>

<p>
From this experience I understand that what I do and where I go is
completely up to me, it is my responsibility and I should create my
own opportunities. What I talked about today may seem childish and
irrational, so are humans. I am happy that I got to think about this
tiny things, most of the time I am too focused on what I have to do
that I can't find time for myself. Maybe writing this here makes me
recognize that I am vulnerable and emotional too.
</p>

<p>
&#x2013; Giovanni
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-05-28 - Lucky and Unlucky</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-05-28.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>28 May 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Hi,
</p>

<p>
today was both the unluckiest and luckiest day that I have memory
of. Let me explain why.
</p>

<p>
This afternoon I had to present a demo of what I have been working on
for my internship. Both a researcher from a company and my professor
were present, it was the opportunity to show my work to my supervisors
so it was a big moment.
</p>

<p>
In the morning I went to university to follow lessons, then went back
home and started preparing some slides. I setup the the local
kubernetes cluster and the operator, everything was compiled,
everything was working. Suddenly my laptop turns off, with no
sign of life, 30 minutes before the presentation.
</p>

<p>
Yes, this happened. All my development setup, the cluster, how could
I demo the program without a computer? You don't.
</p>

<p>
After 0.3 nanoseconds I booted up my desktop PC and began downloading
all the dependencies, cloning all my repositories, logging in on all
my accounts and finishing my slides. I had at least 4 terminals all
running different things in parallel, and I was switching between them
faster than I have ever done. I downloaded Kind and go, setup the
local cluster, deployed the operator and tested it. And somehow&#x2026;
everything worked! The internet connection, the fedora package
manager, all the dependencies were working well without additional
troubleshooting, the local cluster was online and ready, and my
application was working as expected (obviously). I finished installing
the last dependency the moment I joined the zoom call, that was
incredibly close.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-06-05 - Last University lesson</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-06-05.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>05 Jun 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Yesterday I had my last class lecture of my bachelor degree in
computer science. This concludes a period of three years where I
dedicated all my time to studying and mastering my crafts.  From my
part, I rarely skipped a lesson. In fact, I count less than 10 lessons
I did not attend for various reasons often not in my control, I have
always showed up even when I did not feel like going and that kept me
motivated to push through all my exams. Now I will take some time to
reflect on what has been, all while studying for my last three exams.
</p>

<p>
What I am most grateful for is being able to dedicate to my studies
fully, which is really a privilege and it won't happen again, I am on
my own now. In three years I rarely "unfocused" and when that happens
I would feel lost, thankfully I could dedicate my entire wake time and
my energies to programming and studying programming and open source
projects which is so important for me.
</p>

<p>
Did everything go smoothly? Was everything the best it could have
been? Absolutely no, yet I stopped thinking about what could have
been and instead I learned to appreciate what I have now. Probably
about 80% to 90% of my time getting this piece of paper of a degree
was not worth it, I had so many terrible exams where I learned
nothing, yet I did so much more outside university like a graphics
engine, an operating system, I hacked with the Linux kernel for
hundreds of hours and I have developed some expertise through these
projects.
</p>

<p>
If you don't know, Italian universities are very theoretical. I didn't
do many projects, anyone could get this degree with very little
knowledge of programming. Exams are hard, sometimes unreasonably hard
depending on the professor, and the future is really uncertain for
students unless you emigrate to other nations. Such is the situation,
or at least how I am perceiving this right now. You see me complaining
now, however I rarely rant on things; I prefer getting things done
without much talk.
</p>

<p>
Even if I have so much to learn, I now know a little bit more than
before. It never feels enough, but It is progress and I trust the
process.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-06-21 - The world changes, and so do you</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-06-21.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>21 Jun 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I was taking a walk in a park near my room, I often go there when I
want to breathe some fresh air after a long study session or when I
feel anxious. The reason why I go to this specific park is, other than
being easy to reach, the presence of a public book crossing
shelf. There are many of those, scattered across the city, and people
can go there and leave or take any book. If nobody is greedy and
everyone leaves and takes the exact amount, then there would be a
constant number of books always changing. In reality, some people are
more generous than others and overall there is always a good amount of
books, at least 20 in this one. As always, I am curious to see whether
there are new books and if any of them interest me, so I go to the
location. As a side note, I like this place so much that I marked it
and other places in openstreetmap so that their location is registered
for others to use.
</p>

<p>
When I reached the little hose, what I found was a patch of dirt
surrounded by grass. Maybe I was mistaken about the place, so I went
back and forth on the street, but I was not mistaken. Indeed the shelf
was not there anymore, apparently it was decided that It had to be
removed from the park and it's now gone.
</p>

<p>
This reminded me that everything, even good things change. Nothing is
really forever. Obviously this is something I already knew and
experienced, and I accepted it. Likewise, we humans change both as
spices and as individuals in our short lifetime. Previously I was
reading some entries of my diary from three years ago, I noticed that
the things that moved me and the things I did as a consequence of
these were completely different. Yet some things are still the same,
it's always me but the perspective is different and how I perceived
the world is different.
</p>

<p>
When you look back at history you see how so many things change
drastically. We went from horses as a means of transportation to space
rockets in less than a century thanks to human ingenuity. When you
look really back, think about the Roman Empire or civilizations now
lost to time, the changes are so great that it is difficult even to
imagine how the world was at that time. Yet some things are the same,
the mountains that surround my city have been there for
millennial. Once, these mountains were seen as obstacles that you
needed to circumvent to reach other cities. During the first world war
they were seen as a military fortress to protect the border, now they
are seen as nature to protect.
</p>

<p>
I now feel stoic about things changing, I see this as a rule of life
so I don't feel bad when things do change. That works either way for
things that disappear and things that appear. What I can do is to hold
tight what I wish to keep with me longer to delay the inevitable.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-06-24 - The importance of having genuinely fun</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-06-24.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>24 Jun 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
(I am writing this entry the day after since I slept early yesterday)
</p>

<p>
Lately I have been spending the majority of my time studying for my
last university exams. I have been preparing for these exams for at
least two months without breaks, and until recently I followed all the
lessons diligently. In general, when I study something I want to be
completely immersed in the subject and I want to get as many inputs as
possible: youtube videos, books, exercises, I keep thinking about it
day and night. Hence, I never really take "breaks" from studying, just
change or limit my inputs. It comes no surprise that sometimes I feel
exhausted, so I give myself some minutes off to slow down the pace.
</p>

<p>
After a while, this routine of studying from morning until I am too
tired is not healthy and I need to take more time off. Lately I went
too far and now I have a great headache and I have problems sleeping,
consequently I don't have a lot of energies during the day and I have
difficulties concentrating. Always thinking about the same things made
my mind kind of stuck, I needed some kind of distraction. To be
totally honest, I am doing other things such as reading a book about
economics and another about hacker culture, I am learning the lean
programming language and in general I have been reading a lot of math
books, or just taking a walk or trying to sleep more. I found these
activities ineffective to "unstuck" my brain, I needed more powerful
distractions that could take me off my studies. So I thought about
video games.
</p>

<p>
I thought that playing a fast paced, online FPS game would be the
solution. I have not played a game like this in 4+ years and I
wouldn't say I am the type of person to play these types of games. I
also wanted something that could run on very cheap hardware and on
Linux.  After some research, I found <a href="https://xonotic.org/">xonotic</a>: a free classic arena
shooter similar to quake or unreal tournament. I have to say that I
really had a great fun playing this game, I was fully concentrated and
my senses were 100% active in order to react to the fast movement of
the enemies. I haven't felt this adrenaline in a while, additionally
the chat and the soundboards were hilarious and made me laugh. Even if
I was not at the top of the leadeboard, I gave my best and had fun, I
even recorded my matches on a new <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@Giogames-d6f">youtube channel</a>.
</p>

<p>
Playing this game changed my day and I had more energies to do other
things. As someone that really rarely grants himself some time off,
this was a good reset. Most of the time it is difficult to stay
focused on something and I think you should render all distractions
at minimum, that's what I always try to do. Yet a dose of distraction
can also be beneficial, and this experience is a reminder of this.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-06-26</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-06-26.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>26 Jun 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[
<div id="orga5b333e" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/fireworks.jpg" alt="fireworks.jpg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Fireworks</p>
</div>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-07-03 - Willkommen in Linz</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-07-03.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>03 Jul 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Today is my first day in Linz Austria, I will be staying here for two
months to work for a tech company. This opportunity was somewhat
unexpected since I was not actively looking to go abroad, but then the
opportunity came and I decided to go with it.
</p>

<p>
This experience has great personal value for me. First of all, I will
be working in the industry I want to build a career in; I can finally
step out of the University bubble and see what a real day to day job
looks like. Further, I get paid for this so I can be financially
independent which is important.
</p>

<p>
Moreover, I want to see how I handle myself in a completely new
environment. I have been living alone already for three years but I
got used to my life in Trento, I enjoyed quite a stable situation and
it has been a while since I had great changes in my life.
</p>

<p>
I also don't know German, which means I have to translate everything
when I go out since the city does not put much effort helping you. As
soon as I moved in to my building, I had to fill a document with
details about myself for the immigration center; the document was in
German so it took me a while to understand everything that I needed to
write, thankfully it was not too difficult and I asked another person
to review my understanding of the words. Still, why would a document
that immigrants need to sing be in German? English is the universally
known language and chances are that people from other countries know
English. Maybe there is some policy regarding official documents, but
I think this is not helping the person that wants to enter the
country.
</p>

<p>
Once I had the document signed, I needed to bring it to a local
library where I would be registered in the country. The local library
then pointed me to go to the center in the Magistrate, which pointed
me to go to room 1109 where they handled the registration. I have to
say that everything was really fast and the people I talked to knew
where to send me.
</p>

<p>
What was.. unusual.. was how many young people I met during this
process, and while moving. The people I talked to in the Magistrate
were really young, I'd say between 21 and 25 except one which was
older. Even the girl at the city library, and the people in the
tram. This makes me sad seeing that in Italy all the young people are
fleeing the country and who's left are mostly elderly people.
</p>

<p>
Later, I bought my lunch at Eurospar and took a nap. I needed to buy
more things but then it started raining really heavily so I went to a
closer store and bought just the dinner. Even if the trip was a few
hundred meters, my pants and shoes got completely wet, thankfully
there is a dryer I can use in the building. Tomorrow I'll go to a
second hand shop and buy some plates and things to cook at a cheap
price (hopefully) so I can start cooking by myself.
</p>

<p>
I need some sleep now, the previous night I could not sleep at all in
the bus. Yet flixbusses are really nice, I payed a fraction of what I
would have payed if I were to go by train or plane.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-07-04 - Set up</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-07-04.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>04 Jul 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I had a few chores to do today before taking some time to relax since
my arrival here. In particular, I needed to get equipment to cook and
stuff for the bathroom so I can finally take a shower. So, I looked
for shops of second hand items; not only because it is wasteful to buy
brand new items, but mainly because it is cheaper to get used
ones. Most of these types of shops sell clothes but there are some
where you can find anything, so I went out towards the city center.
</p>

<p>
Since the shop I found would only open at 11 am, and I was already
awake at 7, I took some time to explore the city and the path I need to
take to work, I also managed to buy groceries and come back in my room
before 11. Finally I went to this second hand shop, it is close to the
bridge where the tram passes; the shop was full of stuff all on top of
one another, from keyboards to carpets to chairs. Obviously they had
everything I needed, however there was a problem that made the whole
experience uncomfortable and somewhat funny.
</p>

<p>
The owner did not know English, not a single word. I do not know
German, I assumed she didn't even know Italian. So we were stuck with
a great barrier, I tried to communicate with very simple words like
"money?" "cooking" but it was all worthless and confusing&#x2026;
</p>

<p>
After a few minutes, I decided to simply open google translator and
translate what I needed. Things went better: she would point at
some things that I was interested, I pointed to the ones I wanted, and
she wrote the price on a piece of paper. That worked and I got
everything, which includes two plates, a fork, spoon and knife, a pot,
a mug and two bathroom towels. All of this for 8.50 euro! I saved so
much money going there, sadly it was harder than expected.
</p>

<p>
This made me think about how the language barrier is a difficult
obstacle for many people. Imagine how merchants would trade
internationally hundreds of years ago, or Italian cities in the
renaissance, it must have been a similar experience.
</p>

<p>
Obviously it started raining a lot and my second pair of shoes got
completely wet. I already got used to this, but it was funny how so
many people in the city center did not have an umbrella and got
completely wet. Yesterday it rained heavily, and the forecast of today
told the same thing, so wouldn't you think bringing an umbrella would
be a wise idea? Apparently that was not a concern for some people.
</p>

<p>
I came in my apartment for lunch with the newly bought things. Since I
needed to clean everything thoroughly, I didn't cook and I ate a
sandwich instead. I washed and dried my clothes and the bath towels
while I was cleaning the kitchen equipment. A thing I wanted to visit
was the central public library, so I took the tram and a walk to the
library, but I didn't stay a lot of time there since the public WiFi
was not working for me (I was getting SSL error).
</p>


<div id="org768812a" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/linz-city.jpg" alt="linz-city.jpg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>The city center</p>
</div>

<p>
During this time I also bought a physical diary. I have many of these
and they hold great sentimental value for me. Another physical
diary for my Linz adventures seemed a great idea. Obviously I am not
sharing everything publicly, just what I am comfortable telling anyone.
</p>

<p>
Finally, I came home and I could have my (deserved) bath and cook my
first meal. This felt great, I now have everything set up and I can
move my attention into other things. Thankfully, having already lived
alone for three years made me conscious of everything that I need to
live and take care of myself so these two days were easy in terms of
planning.
</p>


<div id="org0e3f846" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/linz-dinner.jpg" alt="linz-dinner.jpg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>The Chef's table</p>
</div>

<p>
While I was cooking I listened to the latest album of Sleeping at Last
"Atlas: Reach". While I was eating I watched "Better call Soul", the
prequel of Braking Bad which I really enjoyed.
</p>

<p>
There is now the sunset so I'll probably take a walk now, then I'll
setup a study plan for my exams.
</p>


<div id="orgab6f4df" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/linz-sunset.jpg" alt="linz-sunset.jpg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Sunset (almost) by the river</p>
</div>

<p>
I didn't manage to be exactly near the river, but I was close. If I
were smarter I would have taken the tram to the bridge, that's a TODO
item for another day.
</p>

<p>
Btw, I think I will start posting updates on my spending so you (and
the me of the future) gets an idea of how much I am spending day by
day.
</p>

<pre class="example">
 Expenses                           ||          
------------------------------------++----------
 expenses:food                      ||   $22.78 
 expenses:household:bathroom        ||    $7.86 
 expenses:household:kitchen         ||    $8.74 
 expenses:household:washing-machine ||    $7.49 
 expenses:legal                     ||   $19.92 
 expenses:non-essential             ||    $4.45 
 expenses:rent                      || $1406.00 
 expenses:travel:arrival            ||   $39.47 
 expenses:travel:public-transport   ||   $60.50 
------------------------------------++----------
                                    || $1577.21 
</pre>

<p>
I use the ledger format to store my transaction, and hledger for the
fancy reports. I will make an explanation of how I use these in the
future.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-07-05 - Stores closed</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-07-05.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>05 Jul 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Today I made my first irrational action since I am here in Linz. I
broke my streak of being a good and responsible stoic and I consciously
did something I would usually never do. Let me tell you the full
story.
</p>

<p>
Last night I didn't sleep too well and I didn't wake up fully rested,
yet I had to start my day anyway. My plan for today was to study
Algorithms and data structures for an exam on September, and get
groceries. The first went really well, I went to the central city
library in the morning, then came back, had lunch and studied in a
common place in my dormitory.
</p>

<p>
This exam is composed of two written parts lasting an entire year, two
projects and a final oral discussing everything prior; I just need to
do the oral and I want to study everything deeper than what is
required, as I always do, since algorithms are one of the most
important areas in computer science. Today I started all the way back
from the basics and studied the big-O notation, its mathematical
properties and how to find the complexity of a recurrence
function. This is not enough and I still need to do many exercises. If
I have some more time I want to prove everything with a proof
assistant like Lean4, I am dreaming of this and hopefully I will start
investigating this soon.
</p>

<p>
This morning I also saw a part of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m2i1UQZ_CGA">interview</a> between Mr. Rip and
Salvatore Sanfilippo the great. He is the creator of Redis and an
influential programmer from Sicily, I will watch the whole interview
slowly since it is two hours long.
</p>

<p>
After I was getting tired with studying in the late afternoon I
thought I could go out to get dinner and get a few days worth of
groceries. However, I was shocked when I discovered that every single
food shop, expect restaurants, were closed during weekends 0.0
</p>

<p>
This is very unusual for me since in Italy all the stores remain
open, and I was used to getting my food on the weekend; but here in a
city of 200 000+ people all the shops were closed. Literally, the only
one open was the eurospar at the station which is 45 minutes for tram
from here. Unbelievable.
</p>

<p>
But I had to take my dinner anyway, so I quickly took the tram toward
the eurospar hoping to get everything I needed. During my movements I
am reading "Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution", a really
great book about the story of the early hackers in the 60' at MIT. I
am really hooked, I also cannot do much else since I cannot use
internet on my phone outside as I have very limited internet usage
outside of Italy in my phone contract.
</p>

<p>
When I finally arrive to the station (after getting a little lost), I
find hundreds of young people - gangster looking - all gathered at the
entrance. Apparently this was really the only place open and everyone
was here to get some drinks&#x2026; so I stood in line.
</p>

<p>
After I could finally enter, I discovered that 80% of the shop was
blocked and the only open area was the one with beer, meat and
fruits&#x2026; this means that I could not get the things that I wanted, so
I took some bananas and went outside.
</p>

<p>
This made me quite dissatisfied, how is it possible that I have no way
to buy basic food in the city? Maybe Italy is not that bad after
all. With this feeling of emptiness, and quite a bit of hunger, I find
myself before a McDoanld's and I made the split decision to enter.
</p>

<p>
Now, I literally never go to McDonald's and I do not understand why
people go there. I can have a better and healthier meal at home for 1
or 2 euros, instead people pay 10 or more of an unhealthy amount of
burghers in a loud place. Yet, here I am taking a burgher myself, only
for this night, while reading today's HackerNews top post - and I
wasn't even full afterwards.
</p>

<p>
I don't feel proud of this at all, I consider it a stupid decision
that I made emotionally and I would have never done it if I took more
time to think. That money could have been spent much wiser in other
things. Anyway, here we are.
</p>


<div id="org66d78c7" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/linz-mc.jpg" alt="linz-mc.jpg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Dinner at McDonald's</p>
</div>

<p>
Expenses so far:
</p>

<pre class="example">
 Expenses                           ||           
------------------------------------++-----------
 expenses:food                      ||    $31.82 
 expenses:food:non-essential        ||     $9.20 
 expenses:household:bathroom        ||     $7.86 
 expenses:household:kitchen         ||     $8.74 
 expenses:household:washing-machine ||     $7.49 
 expenses:legal                     ||    $19.92 
 expenses:non-essential             ||     $4.45 
 expenses:rent                      ||  $1406.00 
 expenses:travel:arrival            ||    $39.47 
 expenses:travel:public-transport   ||    $60.50 
------------------------------------++-----------
                                    ||  $1595.45
</pre>

<p>
Ah btw, happy birthday to me! I almost forgot it.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-07-06 - Writing math proofs</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-07-06.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>06 Jul 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Nothing much to tell today. I spent most of my time studying
Algorithms, right now I need to read and summarize the chapters that I
am missing. This is the most energy demanding part but hopefully I
will be done in a week or two. Once I have all my notes, I just need
to get comfortable explaining the details and the proofs, which
usually takess a lot of time but it is less intense.
</p>

<p>
Today I proved the "Master Theorem" for finding the time complexity of
certain types of recursive functions, it took me at least half an hour
to understand the proof but I finally got it and It is nice. I spent
the rest of the day playing the <a href="https://adam.math.hhu.de/">natural number game</a> where you need to
write proof for the properties the basic operations in the natural
numbers (successor, addition, multiplication&#x2026;). It is very
challenging for me since I am quite new to formal proofs and I need to
build an intuition for how these proof assistant work, but at least I
made some progress.
</p>

<p>
Eventually I want to be able to prove some theorems for cryptography
like RSA and some other fundamental theorems from calculus. I know
that Terence Tao has published a calculus book with Lean4 proofs but I
didn't read it yet.
</p>

<p>
Anyway, tomorrow I will start working at the company, which I will
refer to as D from now on. Hopefully it will go as smoothly as the
last few days have (mostly) been.
</p>

<p>
Expenses so far (same as yesterday):
</p>

<pre class="example">
 Expenses                           ||           
------------------------------------++-----------
 expenses:food                      ||    $31.82 
 expenses:food:non-essential        ||     $9.20 
 expenses:household:bathroom        ||     $7.86 
 expenses:household:kitchen         ||     $8.74 
 expenses:household:washing-machine ||     $7.49 
 expenses:legal                     ||    $19.92 
 expenses:non-essential             ||     $4.45 
 expenses:rent                      ||  $1406.00 
 expenses:travel:arrival            ||    $39.47 
 expenses:travel:public-transport   ||    $60.50 
------------------------------------++-----------
                                    ||  $1595.45
</pre>

<p>
I'll watch another episode of Better Call Saul this night.
</p>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-07-07 - Math riddle</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-07-07.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>07 Jul 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I am happy that everything went great today. I didn't feel stressed or
anxious, I was a bit confused on what to do at the beginning but the
feeling went away and I already feel comfortable in the office.
</p>

<p>
I'll write some more thoughts in the following days, right now I am
puzzled by a riddle written in the blackboard of the office, and it
goes like this:
</p>

<p>
Gauss and Euler are playing a game, there are two secret numberrs \(p\)
and \(s\) between \(2\) and \(99\). Gauss knows the value \(g = p*s\) and Euler knows the value \(e
= p + s\). Then they say to eachother:
</p>

<pre class="example">
Gaus: I don't know p and s
Euler: I am not surprised
Gaus: Now I know
Euled: Now I know too
</pre>

<p>
What are \(p\) and \(s\)?
</p>

<p>
I have been playing with numbers for a few hours but I can't figure
this out!
</p>

<p>
Expenses so far, I marked the refundable things and I will count them
in the total balance until I get the refunds:
</p>

<pre class="example">
 Expenses                           ||           
------------------------------------++-----------
 expenses:food                      ||    $31.82 
 expenses:food:non-essential        ||     $9.20 
 expenses:food:refundable           ||    $10.00 
 expenses:household:bathroom        ||     $7.86 
 expenses:household:kitchen         ||     $8.74 
 expenses:household:washing-machine ||     $7.49 
 expenses:legal:refundable          ||    $19.92 
 expenses:non-essential             ||     $4.45 
 expenses:rent                      ||   $656.00 
 expenses:rent:refundable           ||   $750.00 
 expenses:travel:arrival            ||    $39.47 
 expenses:travel:public-transport   ||    $60.50 
------------------------------------++-----------
                                    ||  $1605.45
</pre>

<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>2025-07-12 - Unbalanced</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/2025-07-12.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>12 Jul 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I officially broke by streak of journaling everyday, it went well for
a few days but I was not diligent enough. The reason being that I
worked a lot and the last few days life has been unbalanced. I want to
talk more about these two topics, starting with work.
</p>

<p>
This was my first week at the company. Even if everything was new to
me, I managed to get used to the system really quickly. By the second
day I was already developing a proof of concept which would help
another research project from one of my team members. If you have ever
done Research and Development, or research work in general, you know
that this is something that takes your mind completely which makes it
difficult to balance work and life. I felt this quite hard: I really
like the programs I am developing and I want to spend the most amount
of time possible thinking about these problems. For context, I am
working on applications that use eBPF programs in kubernetes clusters
for security services like monitoring, fingerprinting, and proxing (I
think I can't give further details). It has some operating systems
programming which is the part I like, and it has some kubernetes /
cloud involved which may be what keeps paying for a roof and food. And
so, I am really invested in my work and I usually overwork more than I
should, and when I come home I still think about the code and what I
could do better. This is partially the reason why I did not write this
diary daily, the other reason being that I come home late and I am
simply mentally tired.
</p>

<p>
If I allowed myself to take proper breaks, maybe my life would be more
balanced and I would be able to consistently write this blog. On the
other hand, there is a strong part of me that really wants to work as
much as possible and spend every bit of my energy to do work, for my
future. In fact, this part of me believes that you can achieve things
and be proud of yourself only by working really hard and by mastering
your crafts. That is what I have been doing for many years to stay
true to this. With this mentality, you may understand that it is
difficult to allow me some time for myself and to rest. However, I
realize the importance of this for my well being, the problem is that
it does not feel good in my mind. In spite of this, this evening I
think I'll take some time off and reflect more on the past week and
months, get things clear and organized.
</p>

<p>
I did not fully explore Linz yet. Today I went running next to the
river, and previously I only briefly visited the main city street. The
rest of my time outside is spent in the road between the apartment and
the office. In my defense, I tried to look for some events in the city
but I don't really care about famous singers or artistic exhibitions,
so I don't have much to do.
</p>

<p>
Expenses so far:
</p>

<pre class="example">
 Expenses                           ||           
------------------------------------++-----------
 expenses:food                      ||    $48.12 
 expenses:food:non-essential        ||     $9.20 
 expenses:food:refundable           ||    $20.00 
 expenses:household:bathroom        ||     $7.86 
 expenses:household:kitchen         ||     $8.74 
 expenses:household:washing-machine ||     $7.49 
 expenses:legal:refundable          ||    $19.92 
 expenses:non-essential             ||     $4.45 
 expenses:rent                      ||   $656.00 
 expenses:rent:refundable           ||   $750.00 
 expenses:travel:arrival            ||    $39.47 
 expenses:travel:public-transport   ||    $60.50 
------------------------------------++-----------
                                    ||   $1631.75
</pre>


<hr />

<p>
Travel: <a href="ephemeris.html">Ephemeris</a>, <a href="../theindex.html">Index</a> 
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
</channel></rss>