<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel>
<title>Giovanni's Diary Surroundings</title>
<link>giovanni-diary.netlify.com/reading/surroundings/surroundings.html</link>
<description><![CDATA[Surroundings is a series of descriptions of places I find myself into. It is a raw translation of what my eyes see looking outward, filtered by my own mind, in the historical period I live in. The purpose of those writings is to provide a testimony of what a place looks like and feels like in a certain moment. It indirectly records what I, Giovanni, notice and pay attention to and feel, in this particular moment of my life. ]]></description>
<item>
<title>Doss Trento</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/reading/surroundings/doss-trento.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>27 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Here I am up Doss Trento, the closest elevation from the city center.
You may recognize this doss by the proud white monument of Cesare
Battisti looking over the valley. The doss feels smaller than expected
from up here, there are two main grass areas: one next to the monument
and another one next to a war museum. I visited the museum a while
ago, displayed were uniforms, weapons and tools used by the people of
this lands during world war 1. The purpose of this entire doss seems
to be to hold the memory of such a terrible past. Some scary weapons
lay on the outside, with some people standing over them as if It were a
bench. Other people come here to walk ther dogs or just to take a
breath.
</p>


<div id="org9d00528" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/doss-trento-view-north.jpeg" alt="doss-trento-view-north.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>View of northern Trento</p>
</div>


<div id="org7cf599f" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/doss-trento-view-south.jpeg" alt="doss-trento-view-south.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>View of southern Trento</p>
</div>


<div id="orga26fd55" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/doss-trento-monument.jpeg" alt="doss-trento-monument.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Monument to Cesare Battisti</p>
</div>


<div id="org07b9c0e" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/doss-trento-map.jpeg" alt="doss-trento-map.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 4: </span>Map of the area</p>
</div>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Go back: <a href="surroundings.html">surroundings</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mount San Martino</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/reading/surroundings/mount-san-martino.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>30 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Mount San Martino (~1400m) is located west of Bleggio Superiore and
east from Val Rendena, in a beautiful place called Giudicarie.  The
whole area of Bleggio is a place rich with history and legends. Once
upon a time, in the medieval age, merchants and popes would travel
through those lands to go north, villages developed, churches were
built. Even to this day, this place still holds the memory of a great
and prosperous time. In modern times, due to industrialization, the
valley of Adige began developing and became the main road to the
north and an important industrial center. Still, this place gained
something else, It is now a peaceful, wonderful place, respectful of
nature and life itself.
</p>

<p>
We begin our hike on the location of Larido, south of Rango (as a
sidenote, Rango is famous for christmas shops) where there are places
to park. The path forward is not certain at the start, since there are
no signs mentioning the mountain top, so with a bit of trust we follow
the only path west going upword.
</p>


<div id="org955fc84" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/mount-san-martino-map.jpeg" alt="mount-san-martino-map.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Map of the hike</p>
</div>

<p>
The hike is a safe one, the overall height difference is 670m but the
rate of change in elevation is smooth across the whole hike, without
any difficult sections. We choose this hike because there is still
snow over 1500m so we planned to stay low (spolier, we still found
some snow in unilluminated areas). After some time, the view opens to
the valley below, looking east. The tops of Bondone and Stivo are very
recognisable, dominating over the other mountains.
</p>


<div id="orgea8cc5d" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/mount-san-martino-fiave.jpeg" alt="mount-san-martino-fiave.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>View of the town of Fiave from the mountain</p>
</div>


<div id="org10970c8" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/mount-san-martino-stivo.jpeg" alt="mount-san-martino-stivo.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>View of the mount Stivo</p>
</div>

<p>
Midway to the top, a grass area opens up. A few tiny, little one-room
houses are scattered here and there, one high up, one far down the
edge. The view here is wonderful, the sun shines, no car noises
can be heard. We spot a youg couple enjoying their breakfast in the
garden, we say hello to them and shared a smile, as everyone does with
strangers.
</p>


<div id="org37591fc" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/mount-san-martino-house.jpeg" alt="mount-san-martino-house.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 4: </span>A beautiful and paceful house</p>
</div>

<p>
All of a sudden we reach the top, where a radio tower replaces
the usual cross we find in mountain tops. We stop for a break and
to have launch and some laughs.
</p>


<div id="org1ad7b7d" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/mount-san-martino-group.jpeg" alt="mount-san-martino-group.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 5: </span>Group photo after reaching the top</p>
</div>


<div id="orgf0c1e0e" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/mount-san-martino-south.jpeg" alt="mount-san-martino-south.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 6: </span>South view</p>
</div>

<p>
Descending here is easy, we take the well made forestale path, and
then we switch to an abandoned one which is barely visible. It had a
magical feel, as if we were in a forgotten forest with witches and
monsters, with dead trees left and right to disorient us.  We came out
alive towards the strada provinciale before taking another path back
to Larido, were everything started.  Before that, we took some time
to play with an horse.
</p>


<div id="orgfd53d4e" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/mount-san-martino-horse.jpeg" alt="mount-san-martino-horse.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 7: </span>Picture of a horse</p>
</div>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Go back: <a href="surroundings.html">surroundings</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>San Marco Garden</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/reading/surroundings/san-marco-garden.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>25 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I find myself in the San Marco Garden. The garden is situated in the
center of the city of Trento, in the oldest part. The park is an odd
but beautiful place, a drop of green in the middle of buildings and
busyness. Surraunded by medieval walls, It feels like this place
is outside our times. The first brave daisies paint the grass,
announcing the start of this year's spring, toghether with many other
colorful flowers on display, with their descriptions on metal plates.
Pigeons are everywhere, to remind me the reality of the situation:
the nature here is human-made, those plants and shiny flowers have no
reasons to be here other than for show, being artificially kept alive
by us humans for our own delight.
</p>

<p>
Being situated in the city center, the park is a busy place, often
used to move from one place of the city to another. Lots of people
are passing by. Sometimes some people stop to take pictures of the
colorful flowers. I belive there is a kindergarden nearby so a few
kids with their families join the others in the garden, bringing
laughts and tears, emotions.
</p>


<div id="orgf762284" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/san-marco-garden-full.jpeg" alt="san-marco-garden-full.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>My view of the garden</p>
</div>

<p>
On my right there is a fountain delivering fresh water. On top of it,
a bird is drinking the water. There are a few bird houses scattered on
the sides of the trees, I can see just one from my position but I believe
there are more since I can hear birds singing all over the garden. A
few ants and flies are moving around silently.
A bigger fountain sits in the middle of the gardan, but with a much
weaker water throughput and It is difficult to reach, just for display.
</p>


<div id="orgec7049f" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/san-marco-garden-fountain.jpeg" alt="san-marco-garden-fountain.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>The fountain on my right</p>
</div>

<p>
Looking closely at the ground, one can find many used cigarettes,
bottle caps, straws and pieces of plastic envelopes. Overall, the garden
is decently clean, unless you start paying attention to the details.
There are those automatic irrigation systems spreaded in the park, I
hope they don't turn on right now (It happened once in another place).
</p>


<div id="org74ec8e3" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/san-marco-garden-cigarettes.jpeg" alt="san-marco-garden-cigarettes.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Cigarettes and bottle caps</p>
</div>


<p>
The colorful houses that surround the park completely block the view
from the mountains. Maybe a glimpse of the Marzola mountain could be
seen from here on a nicer day without clouds. A flag of peace is
displayed from a window of one of the buildings.
The clouds have moved and there is no trace of the Marzola, sadly.
</p>

<p>
A dog and the owner are joining the park, playing with a ball. Although
the dog is more interested in biting the ball, with much focus.
Some drops of water are falling from the sky, the sun is slowly
setting and It is becoming colder.
</p>

<p>
It is the 25 of March 2025, 5:53pm, the spring season started a few
days ago.
</p>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Go back: <a href="surroundings.html">surroundings</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Sant Agata Church</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/reading/surroundings/sant-agata-church.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>26 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Sitting in front of me is Sant'Agata church, or what remains of it.
Despite It's age, being born in the 16th century, the church stands
strong from the ground, challenging time itself.  We rest together
on a "Doss" which is a tall hill or bump from the ground, but too
modest to be considered a mountain, laying between Povo and
Oltrecastello. Everything is quiet here except the birds and the
noise of the cars from the city beneath.
</p>

<p>
Reaching the top of the Doss is simple. From Povo, more specifically
Piazza Manci, one can follow the street going east towards Cimirlo.
At the first opportunity, turn left when you see a SAT sign advertising
a walk reaching Oltrecastello. The trail quickly goes up for the first
10 minutes, and slows down for the remaining 15. Despite the first
half, the path is generous with many benches to let the explorer
catch some breath. Overall, the walk is easily accessible even for
elderly people, I even met two elderly women while I was going up.
An alternative route would be from Oltrecastello, following the
street towards Povo and turning right just after the main piazza
of the town. The path here is shorter but steeper. Obviously, you
could go down from either of the two ways.
</p>


<div id="org7ee1a8d" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/sant-agata-map.jpeg" alt="sant-agata-map.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Map of the path</p>
</div>


<p>
From up here one can enjoy a good view of Adige's valley, with Its
urban areas and urban noises, expecially the southern parts of Trento.
Instead, the small fraction of Borino and Cimirlo are perfectly
visible in their entirety, a rare sight since they are often hidden by
this same doss. Surrounding the hill stand the mount of Marzola on the
South-East, mount Celva from east, mount Calisio on the northen side
and the valley on the west. The snow on top of Paganella and Bondone
can be appreciated even during the spring, although this year the snow
has been very shy.
</p>



<div id="orge8e4aaa" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/sant-agata-landscape.jpeg" alt="sant-agata-landscape.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>View of the valley from the top</p>
</div>

<p>
Up here there is a flat grass area where you can enjoy the view and
some fresh air, with planty of benches and space to rest. Most of
the area is now inaccessible because of some escavations beteath the
ground. A long long time ago there was a fortress here ment to
protect the city from attacks coming from Valsugana. When the
fortress was not necessary anymore, It got dismantled but the
foundations still remains.
</p>


<div id="org2bd843e" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/sant-agata-site.jpeg" alt="sant-agata-site.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Archeological site</p>
</div>

<p>
Dominating the area stands a modest church made of stone and
concrete. The look of the church is very simple, with only some
framing around the two windows on the side of the wooden door at the
front of the house faicing west. The walls lack any kind of decoration,
displaying all ruthless of time like an old person. A hollow structure
on the roof hints of a bell lost to time. Despite It's size, the
church catches the attention and the imagination of the people coming
up here, wondering of the devoted and hard working people who created
it in a past era.
</p>


<div id="org56e2939" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/sant-agata-church.jpeg" alt="sant-agata-church.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 4: </span>The church view from west</p>
</div>

<p>
Peeking at the windows, the interior looks as abandoned as the
exterior. A wooden floor with some benches fills the empty space,
hidden by a layer of dust and the lack of sun light. On the back
sleeps what used to be an altar, retired from Its important job,
now discredited and disrespected.
</p>


<div id="org649f920" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/sant-agata-inside.jpeg" alt="sant-agata-inside.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 5: </span>Peeking at the window</p>
</div>

<p>
A good variety of flowers and plants surround the church, keeping
spring alive. The green grass is painted with colors of violet, yellow
and white.
</p>


<div id="org08df8e2" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/sant-agata-flowers.jpeg" alt="sant-agata-flowers.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 6: </span>Some bright flowers</p>
</div>

<p>
It is the 26 of March 2025, 6:11pm.
</p>


<div id="orgc609bf5" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/sant-agata-church-far.jpeg" alt="sant-agata-church-far.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 7: </span>The church from the back</p>
</div>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Go back: <a href="surroundings.html">surroundings</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
</channel></rss>