<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel>
<title>Giovanni's Diary Ephemeris</title>
<link>giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/ephemeris.html</link>
<description><![CDATA[Ephemeris (ἐφημερίς) is an ancient greek word meaning diary, journal. In astronomy, ephemeris refers to a book of tables describing the trajectory of astronomical objects. Here I will keep a sort of public diary with various thoughts and stuff I find interesting for the record.]]></description>
<item>
<title>03-04-2025</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/03-04-2025.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>03 Apr 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I did so many things this week, I don't know where to start.
</p>

<p>
I switched my window manager from i3 to <a href="https://github.com/San7o/dwm">dwm</a>. The cool thing about dwm
is that there is no configuration file, instead you have to change
the C cource code and recompile it. Moreover, dwm is very very
minimal and for most of the things you would need to write custom code,
such as full screen, startup programs and different tiling arrangements.
It is possible to customize it because it is very minimali, abour 2000
lines of code, which is amazing. I didn't read the entire source yet
but I will soon because It is very educational.
</p>

<p>
Another thing, I downloaded Wikipedia, at least some sections of it.
You can download wikipedia to read It offline, and I REALLY like this.
I am becoming more and more independent from the internet every day and
I am enjoying my offline sessions. I have written <a href="../programming/offline-programming.html">offline programming</a>
where I talk about this, I used kiwis to download and view the
compressed wikipedia data.
</p>

<p>
I tried to get into space photography by downloading some images from
JWST and edited them. You can download the .fits file from the <a href="https://mast.stsci.edu/portal/Mashup/Clients/Mast/Portal.html">mast</a>
portal, then you need to fix the colors with some stretch filters.
I used <a href="https://siril.org/">siril</a> for this, which is very powerful but I would prefer
something simpler. I then exported the modified .fits into .tif and
added colors with gimp. The result is not that great but It's a start.
</p>


<div id="org22b7139" class="figure">
<p><img src="./images/jwst-ngc-3132.jpeg" alt="jwst-ngc-3132.jpeg" width="600px" align="center" />
</p>
<p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>NGC 3132 Nebula</p>
</div>

<p>
Yesterday there was the nintendo direct where they announced the
switch 2. I am not a really big fan of Nintendo, being a PC gamer
for my whole life, but the interesting news is that Silk Song exists
and FromSoftware will release a new game similar to bloodborne in style&#x2026;
exclusive for the nintendo switch&#x2026; (sight). Also two new chapters
of deltarune (which I never player but I want to since It is very short).
</p>

<p>
I have been writing machine learning algorithms, such as <a href="https://gist.github.com/San7o/4bfe69a9e1eb251d5267d8b74ff73dda">KNN</a> and the
<a href="https://gist.github.com/San7o/da2efc84eb3e7c8bdbefbd540c8cfbea">perceptron</a>. I am particularly enjoying the math behind everything.
</p>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Go back: <a href="ephemeris.html">ephemeris</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>16-03-2025</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/16-03-2025.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>16 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I was taking a walk in my neighbourhood, there is not much too see
here. A couple of small parks, some triees, and mostly residential
houses. Yesterday I was watching a live of Prod. in real time, he was
just answering some questions from chat. He is such an interesting
and unique person, let me elaborate. Some people know him for his
philosophy videos, I belive he has a formal education in philosophy
and he often records his walks where he openly shared hit thoughts.
He lives a simple life in the mountain, with little to no human
contact or even electricity. Some other people know him for his
emacs videos: he is a maintainer of some well-known pacakges and he is
surely very knowledgable about his emacs-craft. He brings this two
worlds togheter, this is why I think he is so unique.
I started to watch his emacs videos and became interested into the
philosophy ones. What strikes me is his self aweareness. Just by
talking, he uncovered some of my own inner hazards and helped me
get more aware of them.
</p>

<p>
[ Here I have redacted some pages where I reflect about myself, I
am still unsure on how much to share here so I will redact this for
now ]
</p>

<p>
Another point of reflection of this walk was history and searching
through old stuff. In the park where I usually go there is a small
wooden shelf under some stone structure. It is one of those shelfes
where people may take or leave any book. I always stop there to see
new books and If something interests me I would take It home for
some time. Some of the books are narrative, some of them are
didactical books, most of them are very old. What fascinates me is how
those pieces of paper can open a window into the past and look at
the world from a totally different prospective. For example, there
was a local newspaper from a lot of time ago, It was one of the
first with colored ink. It looked like from another era, totally
another style. I imagined how people reading this newspaper looked
like and I find It peaceful. I am attracted to a simpler life,
and I enjoy those thoughts.
</p>

<p>
[ Here I redacted some more pages, but basically I was getting
inspired to start writing some stories ]
</p>

<p>
Anyway, I am heading back home right now. I updated my todo list with
some stuff.
</p>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Go Back: <a href="ephemeris.html">ephemeris</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>19-03-2025</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/19-03-2025.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>19 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I was reading the post "On the Stoic harmony with nature" of Prod
where he talks of phylosophy, I wanted to save It here for the record
because It was such an interesting read:
</p>

<p>
In Greece we have a saying that comes to us from antiquity: “nothing
bad not intermixed with good” (ουδέν κακόν αμιγές καλού). A liberal
translation is “there is no pure evil in this world as everything we
find that is bad always has some good mixed into it.” The opposite is
also true, namely, that all good things have some bad inherent to them.
</p>

<p>
[&#x2026;]
</p>

<p>
In nature things happen when they are meant to. Consider how trees
blossom when their spring arrives, bears hibernate during winter, rain
drops when there are clouds, and so on. No phenomenon can be decoupled
from its fundamentals and, by extension, no event can be independent
of the totality of phenomena. The same is true for the human condition,
though we may lack that kind of patience in our deeds to see how some
eventuality is the result of dynamics that build up over time.
</p>

<p>
[&#x2026;]
</p>

<p>
The Greek word for “nature” is “physis” (φύσις) which refers to things
that grow. They develop organically, as noted above, and have a life
of their own that is couched in terms of the cosmic continuum of life:
they are all coexistent and interdependent. To live in accordance with
nature, then, is to go with the flow of the prevailing conditions,
else to be adaptable. When trees cannot grow directly upward because
some obstacle is in their way, they grow sideways, circumventing the
problem.
</p>

<p>
Compare this to the attitude of forcing things to happen, of declaring
our wants, and trying to implement them regardless of the prevailing
conditions. If the tree insists on only going straight up, then it
will perish. Same principle for humans. What would my life be like
had I insisted on becoming a footballer and did not show the requisite
adaptability to try new things and to ultimately find value in them?
I would probably be miserable the whole time, as I would be fighting
against forces I could not overcome, never to realise my goal, and
never to have the necessary openness to take in what the world was
showing me.
</p>

<p>
End note: thank you Prod for your wisdom.
</p>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Go Back: <a href="ephemeris.html">ephemeris</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>23-03-2025</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/23-03-2025.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>23 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
I just wanted to share a thing that made me laugh for some time. I
am currently developing a kubernetes application for my ""internship"",
most of the code is in go, and some is in c. I am not an expert in go,
however the application is INCREDIBLY slow to compile and it weights
A LOT for being just a simple client that makes some api calls to
kubernetes. So, I was reporting this to one of my "supervisors":
</p>

<pre class="example">
Me:
The only complaint I have at the moment is that building the operator
inside the docker container before pushing It to the local repository
takes 105 seconds on average on my laptop (i3-1110G4 CPU) and it
weights 92M which is outrageous (by comparison, my linux kernel 6.11.4
image is 16M), and I am using the default makefile from operator-sdk...
I guess this is because operator-sdk downloaded a big number of
dependencies but I wonder if the application actually needs all of them
or if they can be compiled once and dynamically linked later to speed
up compile times.
</pre>

<p>
I felt this was a reasonable thing to complain. I got this in response:
</p>

<pre class="example">
Well, I see your point, but it's considered a "feature" of Go to
produce a single binary, which includes all dependencies, but this
also makes the binaries huge :'D
</pre>

<p>
A FEATURE? I really don't know if I should take this language
seriously or just laught at It, beacuse many things are just laughable.
Being able to dynamically link executable has always been one of the
most basic things, It is incredible to me that people consider go as
a language for system programming. Maybe I am just too used to C, but
com' on I cannot have the most simple client of 92MB!
I still have the best intentions of keep learning and write ideomatic
code in go, maybe I just have to understand that modern software has
to suck to become a real go programmer.
</p>

<p>
Also I call this ""intenship"" with many quotes because I am basically
developing this application completely on my own, my teacher is not
even answering my mails. Many of my fellow colleagues are in the same
situation. Still, I was not surpriced since I always think realistically
and honestly I didn't expect much from university, but It surely is
sad. The funny thing is that the internship was supposed to happen with
a company, but then they said It could not continue with them for
various legal reasons (I had to move to the USA) so I am proceeding to
develop what I was suppoed to on my own.
</p>

<p>
Emacs lisp is very cool, I am writing tiny-rss and I am having a lot
of fun. Firther, today I have redesigned by blog and It looks awesome,
exactly what I wanted! It's really really simple, which I find
aesthetically pleasing.
</p>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Go Back: <a href="ephemeris.html">ephemeris</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
<title>24-03-2025</title>
<link>https://giovanni-diary.netlify.app/ephemeris/24-03-2025.html</link>
<author>Giovanni Santini</author>
<pubDate>24 Mar 2025 00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[<p>
Today I stumbled across some really interesting things and I wanted to
share it via this document. If you know me, I am subscribed to quite a
number of mailing lists, one of them being gmane announce. There isn't
a particular reason why I subscribed to this other than curiosity,
messages are rare so It does not bother me.
</p>

<p>
Today a new mailing list was registered for the community around
XEphem. Now, I didn't know what was XEphem prior to reading this
mailing list, but now I am super happy to have discovered it. EXphem
is a "scientific-grade interactive astronomical ephemeris package".
The word Ephemeris comes from greek and It means diary or journal.
In astronomy, It refers to a book of tables describing the trajectory
of astronomical objects. Those books were used and are still used
today (in a more modern fashion) to navigate the sky and to study
celestial bodies.
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://xephem.github.io/XEphem/Site/xephem.html">XEphem</a> is a powerful MIT licensed software with so many
functionalities and a look from the 90', you know this is a good
software. Even though It is practically useless to me, I started
playing with the program. Is is packaged on variaous linux
distributions and even on other operating systems such as FreeBSD and
Solaris. It looks amazing to me, I encourage you to take a look at it,
It is full of functionalities. Also the program is written in C,
beautiful C.
</p>

<p>
I then read the wikipedia page and discovered so many things. First,
cilivizations have been making ephemeris since the Babylonians in the
1st millennium BC. Moreover, the term "epoch" in astronomy refers to
a moment in time used as a reference point for some other astronomical
quantity, what is interesting is that the calendars used in astronomy
are not the same as the terrestrial ones, so sometimes there are
funny dates such as January 0.
</p>

<p>
Overall, it was fun going on a different place where I know close to
nothing about and be intrigued this much like a kid.
</p>

<p>
Some other interesting things. Someone made a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/emacs/comments/1jhjgnu/the_book_of_the_church_of_emacs_satirical_ten/">funny reddit post</a> about
the 10 rules of the emacs church that was fun to read. Also, another
blogger I follow shared some photos of flowers in his city and I feel
inspired to do the same in the following days.
</p>

<p>
One last thing. Today Linux 6.14 released and the usual message from
Linus made me laugh:
</p>

<pre class="example">
So it's early Monday morning (well - early for me, I'm not really a
morning person), and I'd love to have some good excuse for why I
didn't do the 6.14 release yesterday on my regular Sunday afternoon
release schedule. 

I'd like to say that some important last-minute thing came up and
delayed things. 

But no. It's just pure incompetence. 
</pre>

<p>
&#x2014;
</p>

<p>
Go back: <a href="ephemeris.html">ephemeris</a>
</p>
]]></description>
</item>
</channel></rss>